How can somebody tell if they're being
lied to? It's funny that you ask. I
actually wrote a book called The CIA
Insider's Guide to Lying and Lie
Detection.
Um there are a couple of physical tells.
People will look down when answering or
they'll look up as if they're reading a
script that they're preparing for
themselves in their minds. They fidget,
they clear their throat, which is a
delaying tactic even just for a second.
Um
and the deeper you go into a
conversation, if they lose their train
of thought or contradict themselves,
it's because they can't keep the lie
straight. So going into a conversation,
let's take it two ways. One where you
know the person's going to lie to you
and the other one where
you catch them in a lie mid-sentence.
If if let's just say you catch someone
doing something. Let's just say you
catch your partner cheating on you. And
you know that they're going to lie to
you about this.
When you go into that conversation, like
what's the playbook? You know, as
Sergeant Joe Friday used to say, "Just
the facts, ma'am."
Just hit them with the facts. Listen,
I've been in this situation more than
once.
And when when they immediately go to
gaslighting, you know you've got them.
"Are you cheating on me? You are
mentally ill, you know that? You are
mentally ill. Okay, so you are cheating
on me."
You know, they just go over the top in
defense. And then is the goal to
expose them or is the goal to just prove
your point and then walk away and not
That's it right there.
Prove your point, walk away. You can't
go back in time. You're not going to
convince them to take responsibility for
their actions. You have to immediately
reset yourself
to self-protection.
That's what it comes down to. You know,
you mentioned Andrew Bustamante, I love
him. He's been on the show a few times.
I know you guys have had your
differences.
One of the things I learned from him
about lying, and I'd love to get your
thoughts, is it's about pattern
recognition. Like, you have to
consistency with someone to see how they
behave, and if they start to behave a
little differently or speak differently,
then there's a chance they may be lying.
Like, is that Would you say Would you
agree with that as a good tactic? Yeah,
I agree with that. And you know, one of
the one of the best examples is uh in
Godfather II between Michael Corleone
and Fredo, his older but less uh less
able brother.
Um
there's one scene where where Michael
First of all, Michael is angry at Fredo
because of the way Fredo questioned him
in the presence of Moe Greene, if you
remember, over the sale of a of a casino
in Las Vegas.
And then um later in the film,
uh Michael asks Fredo if he knows
so-and-so. And he says, "No, I don't
know him. I never met him." And then
still later,
he mentions that person. Fredo mentions
the person that he claimed not to know,
and said that they went all over Havana
together, and that that guy knows all
the best clubs in Havana.
That's how Michael knew that Fredo had
had um
turned on him. And he gave him sort of
the kiss of Judas and said, "I knew it
was you, Fredo."
And it was because of the
change in in Fredo's pattern of
responding to his brother's questions.
Yeah, because
you're so right, cuz the way I I
understand it as well is it's like you
you mentioned the delays, and if
somebody's clearing their throat, or if
they contradict themselves,
but somebody might just talk like that,
where they stutter, you know, often, no
matter if they're telling the truth or
not. But if they then they But the truth
is the truth.
And that won't or that shouldn't change.
So, if you're mid-conversation with
somebody and you catch them in a lie,
like how do you
take the conversation further so that
either you get them to admit that they
were lying if they're not like some sort
of sociopath or
um
you prove your point and you can walk
away. It depends on the person that
you're arguing with or debating. If if
we're talking about a cheating spouse,
no, I I wouldn't I wouldn't call her on
the lie. I would certainly make a note
of it, probably a written note, and then
look for the best divorce attorney money
could buy, which is exactly what I did.
Um
if it's if it's something professional,
at the CIA, if you're, you know, trying
to recruit a spy to steal a secret,
everybody's going to be lying to you.
And so, you have to sort of take that
into consideration. But then, you know,
you have tools at the CIA that you don't
have in in regular life. Like
I think this guy lies to me all the
time. I think he's lying about his
access. So, I'm going to strap him to
the polygraph, and we're going to get to
the bottom of this today.
And if he's lying, he's cut off. He's
fired. We call it terminated, but it's
an unfortunate word. That just means
he's fired, and we we end our
relationship.
If it's a friend, well, you know, make a
mental note. So-and-so is not reliable.
He's lying to me. I know he's lying to
me. I generally don't call people out on
lying except when I was at the agency
and it was a source lying to me.
I'd call them out then. And I think
people that are either lied to or
they're manipulated or they start to go
down these echo chambers, and they don't
even realize it.
Like how does that happen? Yeah.
In a I I
I think
probably the easiest way to describe it
is
is when people feel that they can get
away with their lies or they feel like
they're smart enough that they can build
up a lie and then maintain the lie.
George Santos, this former congressman,
he was congressman for 15 minutes from
Long Island.
He was a serial fabulist. He lied about
literally everything in life.
Literally everything.
And
you know, it caught up with him and he
ended up in prison and then he got like
seven years. He was in prison for a few
months and and Trump pardoned him.
But
you can't build a life on lies. It's not
sustainable. It's eventually going to
just
all come tumbling down. And I think that
people who lie
if they're not careful, they'll be like,
"Oh, what's the danger of a little white
lie here and there?"
And then if that becomes your
personality, then you just become known
as a liar, which isn't good. My first
station chief told me one time at the
agency, "Never ever lie to medical,
security or finance
because not only will they ruin your
career,
they can put you in prison."
And he said, "And I'll add to that,
never lie to me."
And I I always thought those were good
words to live by. Yeah, and bringing it
in, speaking of cheating, I mean,
there's a rule that I have
that I if I find out you're like
actively cheating on your spouse,
emotionally, physically, I don't care
what it is, like I won't keep you in my
circle whatsoever because if you're
doing that to the person that you're
like sleeping with and laying next to,
like what are you going to do to me?
Yeah, exactly right. I feel exactly the
same way. You're somebody that strikes
me
you'd be hard
to manipulate based on your experience,
what you've learned, what you survived.
What's the easiest type of person who
often gets manipulated? Someone who has
an identifiable vulnerability.
Vulnerability is an important word at
the CIA. A vulnerability can mean almost
anything. Anything that can be exploited
to get you to do what I want.
So, maybe the vulnerability is
you want more money.
It's as easy as that. You just want more
money.
And so, I give you a monthly salary and
in exchange you give me information.
But, the vulnerability could be
something as genuine as
you just really, really love your kids.
And you want your kids to go to
Harvard, let's say, instead of, you
know, the local college in Cameroon or
wherever we happen to be.
I'll get your kids into Harvard.
But, you have to do what I what I want
you to do.
Another vulnerability may be, um,
you got passed over for promotion one
too many times and you're so pissed off
at your boss that you want to get
revenge on him.
And so, you'll give me
classified information just to screw
your boss.
I mean, usually it's money. Sometimes
it's love of family. There was one guy
who was very well placed who gave me the
kitchen sink because his wife had breast
cancer and he really, really wanted her
to go to the Mayo Clinic.
And so, we put her in the Mayo Clinic.
Yeah, so it's it's all about
vulnerabilities and and not in a bad
way.
I just need to identify something that
you want.
I give it to you and in exchange you
give me what I want. Yeah, because at
the end of the day it's finding out what
drives them and what motivates them
to move forward and using
to your advantage. That's exactly right.
What's been something that you've
done over the course of your life when
you've manipulated somebody that you
look back and you feel bad you feel bad
about? Yeah, there was one person
professionally
lovely lady, older lady. She's long dead
now.
I I was working with a source
who was so sensitive
I could not risk meeting him
in
hotels or restaurants.
We just could not be seen in public
together.
So, what we would normally do
would be to meet at 2:00 in the morning.
I would find some deserted place
like the parking lot of a closed factory
at 2:00 in the morning and we would meet
there.
And then I I decided that for security
reasons, you know, any cop could be
driving through the parking lot at any
given time just to make sure kids aren't
there, you know, doing drugs or breaking
windows or whatever
that even meeting at the parking lot at
2:00 in the morning was too risky. So, I
wanted to rent a safe house. Well,
why would an accredited diplomat be
renting an apartment?
Right? I mean, that you can't do that.
That would raise all kinds of red flags.
That would identify me as a CIA officer.
So, I had to recruit what's called a
safe house keeper.
I recruit somebody whose sole job it is
to just go out and rent me an apartment
in his or her name.
Keep it clean. Keep it stocked with, you
know, water.
And I use it one night a week for 2
hours.
And otherwise, it just sits empty.
And this woman just did not want to do
it.
And I cajoled and I argued and I
sweet-talked and
she finally agreed to do it.
And then um
and then she had like like some kind of
nervous breakdown.
Like she didn't even know what I was
going to use it for. I think she
probably thought I was cheating on my
wife and that's why I wanted this, you
know, Pierre et Terre. That wasn't it at
all.
But um
she ended up
having some sort of a breakdown and she
had to leave the country and move back
to the United States and her family took
care of her. And I always wondered if
if that was because I pressured her too
much. Are you taught to not have remorse
or regret when you do things like that?
And you really convince yourself. I
mean, the whole culture convinces you
that that that we're the good guy the
good guys.
We're all the good guys. We're do This
is This is God's work. We're doing it
for Uncle Sam and to keep Americans safe
and
you know, don't ever question yourself.
We're the good guys.